<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article id="bossa-manifesto" class="whitepaper">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Bossa Manifesto</title>
    <corpauthor>The BigBross Team</corpauthor>
    <abstract> 
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <para>
        In this white paper we describe the philosophy behind Bossa,
        the powerful, lightweight and free (as in freedom) workflow
        engine written in Java. We briefly explain what we call
        workflow, how to represent workflows using Petri nets and how
        an application is designed to use Bossa's workflow services.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
      <holder>OpenBR Sistemas S/C Ltda.</holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

<sect1 id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <para>
    Bossa is a workflow engine written in Java. The engine is very
    fast and lightweight, without sacrificing functionality. Its main
    strengths are the very expressive Petri net based notation it uses
    to define workflows and the powerful resource selection
    mechanisms it provides. Also, it is free software licensed under
    the GNU GPL.
  </para>

  <para>
    Bossa does not requires a RDBMS and is very simple to use and to
    integrate with java applications. Actually, it was
    <emphasis>designed</emphasis> to be embedded. Therefore, Bossa is
    organized as a library to be used by server side applications
    (especially web oriented ones) that need workflow services.
  </para>

  <para>
    The characteristic that makes Bossa at the same time simple and
    powerful is the clear separation between <emphasis>workflow
    logic</emphasis> and <emphasis>application logic</emphasis>. We
    believe that, as RDBMSs abstract the data storage and retrieval
    concerns of an application, the workflow of the business process
    being automated should also be abstracted.
  </para>

  <para>
    In this white paper we describe the philosophy behind Bossa. We
    start explaining what we call workflow in <xref
    linkend="workflow"/>. Then, we show how to represent workflows
    using Petri nets in <xref linkend="petri-nets"/>. Finally, we
    describe how an application is designed to use Bossa's workflow
    services in <xref linkend="bossa"/>.
  </para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="workflow">
  <title>Workflow</title>

  <para>
    Within any organization, people will interact with each other to
    get their jobs done. Each one of them may have his or her personal
    list of tasks to be performed. George has to find potential
    customers and file entries for them in a database. Then, Gwen will
    get in touch with the customer. Later, Paul will write a project
    to the customer, and Alice will review it. We can see here that
    their work is flowing. Each person does his job and passes
    something to others so they can do their part.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>Workflow</emphasis> is the name of the total or partial
    automation of a process, that is, a set of rules that govern the
    sequence of activities to get a bigger and collaborative work
    done, involving several participants.
  </para>

  <para>
    Usually the term "workflow" is used with more broad meanings. The
    more common alternate meanings relate to the information exchange
    between the participants of a collaborative work.
    <emphasis>Document management systems</emphasis> are usually
    called workflow systems, mostly because they provide means of
    information exchange and usually do so in an ordered
    manner. <emphasis>Groupware systems</emphasis> are sometimes
    called workflow systems by largely the same reasons, organized
    information exchange.
  </para>

  <para>
    We are not claiming that document management and groupware systems
    are not <emphasis>capable</emphasis> of performing workflow, but
    we believe that handling documents or messages between users is
    not necessarily a concern of workflow systems. Workflow systems
    track activities and helps the right people do the right activity
    at the right time, without regards to the information exchanged.
  </para>

  <para>
    Of course, information exchange <emphasis>is</emphasis> necessary
    for every collaborative application, but we see it as another
    concern, as workflow itself is. Applications should leave their
    data storage needs to a DBMS, their presentation needs to a servlet
    container, their workflow needs to a workflow management system
    and their information exchange needs to a document management
    system. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Bossa aims to provide workflow services in the simplest way
    possible, without sacrificing any power. Therefore, Bossa is
    totally oblivious of the type of data that it is being processed,
    manipulated or exchanged by the application. Bossa only concerns
    itself with the sequence of activities and with the right people
    to perform them.
  </para>

  <para>
    Under our definition of workflow, virtually every conceivable
    collaborative application, and even some non-collaborative one,
    needs workflow services. Since Bossa provides these services in a
    lightweight and unobtrusive manner, we open the possibility of
    workflow <emphasis>everywhere</emphasis>.
  </para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="petri-nets">
  <title>Petri Nets and Workflow</title>

  <para>workflow definition</para>
  <para>petri nets</para>
  <para>workflow as petri nets.  <xref linkend="purchase"/></para>

  <figure id="purchase">
    <title>A purchase department case type.</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata align="center" fileref="purchase.png"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <phrase>The Petri net diagram of the purchase case type.</phrase>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>high level petri nets</para>
  <para>colored</para>
  <para>weighted edges</para>
  <para>details: resources</para>
  <para>An example: a task of the IC process</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="bossa">
  <title>Bossa</title>

  <para>a</para>
</sect1>



<sect1 id="overview">
  <title>Overview</title>


  <para>
    We will present a brief description:

    <variablelist>

     <varlistentry>
      <term>Bossa</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  This module provides... 
	</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
